<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
           <titleStmt>
               <title> <q>Manuka</q> </title>
               <author> "Roslyn" (Margaret A. Sinclair) </author>
           </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
              <edition>Transcribed and edited by Philip Steer</edition>
          </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <publisher>Elliot Stock</publisher>
               <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
               <date>1897</date>
           </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>"Roslyn" [Sinclair, Margaret A.]. <hi rend="italic">The Huia's Homeland, and Other Poems.</hi> London: Elliot Stock, 1897, p. 80. </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> Transcribed, edited, and encoded as part of Settler Environments, which is supported by the Marsden Fund Council from Government funding, managed by Royal Society Te Apārangi. </p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
       <body>
          <lg>
              <l> Acres on acres of low, hilly, poor land </l>
              <l> Is the Manuka’s <note> A species of myrtle, also known as tea tree. A low-growing tree that typically grows on poor soils. </note> peculiar domain; </l>
              <l> Acres on acres like heath on the moorland, </l>
              <l> White with its blossom, like snow on the plain. </l>
          </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Acres on acres to battle a path through, <note> Mānuka commonly grows in dense thickets. </note></l>
               <l> Growing o’erhead like the tall pampas-grass, </l>
               <l> Wirily branched with prickly foliage; </l>
               <l> Woe worth the day when the stranger shall pass! </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Acres on acres, and acres on acres, </l>
               <l> Fire hath swept clean through the length of the land; </l>
               <l> But the Manuka will ne’er be demolished </l>
               <l> Until old Neptune comes over the strand. <note> Mānuka readily grows on land that has been cleared for pasture; the poem imagines that only inundation by the sea will prevent it from flourishing. </note> </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Acres on acres like heath o’ the moorland, </l>
               <l> White with its blossom, like snow on the plain; </l>
               <l> For the fair sunlighted land of the Maori </l>
               <l> Is the Manuka’s peculiar domain. </l>
           </lg>
       </body>
   </text>

</TEI>
