<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
           <titleStmt>
               <title> <q>On a Tree Stump in Inch Clutha</q> </title>
               <author> Dugald Ferguson </author>
           </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
              <edition>Transcribed and edited by Philip Steer</edition>
          </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <publisher> James Horsburgh </publisher>
               <pubPlace> Dunedin </pubPlace>
               <date>1897</date>
           </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> Ferguson, Dugald.  <hi rend="italic">Poems of the Heart.</hi> Dunedin: James Horsburgh, 1897, pp. 47-48. </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> Transcribed and encoded as part of "Settler Literature and Environmental Change in Australia and New Zealand," Marsden Fund Standard Grant 19-MAU-022 (Te Apārangi Royal Society of New Zealand). </p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
       <body>
           <lg>
               <l> Where stately Clutha’s arms enfold </l>
               <l> Her island <note> Inch Clutha is an island in the Clutha River/Mata-Au, located in the South Island of New Zealand. </note> round is to be seen </l>
               <l> A tree stump marvellous to behold, </l>
               <l> So vast in girth, that what had been </l>
               <l> A tree so mighty, one might well </l>
               <l> Deplore what cause there was to fell. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> But anger soon with sorrow blends, </l>
               <l> When told what sent its sentence forth, </l>
               <l> That had no place in paltry ends </l>
               <l> Connected with its market worth </l>
               <l> (That wields o’er men such potent law, </l>
               <l> And doomed it to the woodman’s saw). </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> A sad personage, with nature mean, </l>
               <l> Whose charge the workmen were, to vent </l>
               <l> Against its owner his vile spleen </l>
               <l> Had the tree felled for this intent; </l>
               <l> His mean soul pleased, when on the ground </l>
               <l> He heard its thundering shock resound. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> But for such ill-timed prank I wot, </l>
               <l> Its top umbrageous tow’ring vast </l>
               <l> Might yet on high long proudly float, </l>
               <l> And on the ground its shadow cast, </l>
               <l> With zealous care, guarded from harm, </l>
               <l> As a prized object on the farm. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> For it was once a tree of fame, </l>
               <l> When high it towered o’er the glade; </l>
               <l> And travellers from a distance came, </l>
               <l> And its vast form in awe surveyed, </l>
               <l> As with huge trunk, and mighty limb, </l>
               <l> It tow’red a forest Anakim. <note> Anakim. A race of giants mentioned in the Bible (e.g. Deuteronomy 1:28). </note> </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Ere yet the ruthless Pakeha <note> Pakeha. Pākehā are settlers of British or European descent. </note> </l>
               <l> Appeared with desolating axe, </l>
               <l> And tangled brakes, where chance some pah <note> Pah. A pā is a Māori fortified settlement. </note> </l>
               <l> Was reared mid bordering scrub and flax, </l>
               <l> With echoing strokes felled down and cleared, </l>
               <l> Its towering form there long was reared. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Around its top, an object marked, </l>
               <l> Ten thousand storms had haply raved, </l>
               <l> With howling blasts and lightnings forked, </l>
               <l> That still unscathed had all been braved, </l>
               <l> Till treach’rous act, from dastard foe, </l>
               <l> Its mighty form at length laid low. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> And of the tree late in that place, </l>
               <l> Whose wealth of timber gave such cause </l>
               <l> For wonder, now is found no trace. </l>
               <l> The stump but shows what once it was; </l>
               <l> And thistles now suffice to hide </l>
               <l> What lately was the forest’s pride. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Like it, the man, who once in pride, </l>
               <l> His name “writ large” upon the earth, </l>
               <l> With wealth and substance spreading wide, </l>
               <l> And yet of useful works was dearth; </l>
               <l> And that he lived, but tells alone, </l>
               <l> A costly monumental stone. </l>
           </lg>
       </body>
   </text>
    
</TEI>
