<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
           <titleStmt>
               <title> <q>The Forty-Mile Bush</q> </title>
               <author> “Austral” (Anne Glenny Wilson) </author>
           </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
              <edition>Transcribed and edited by Philip Steer</edition>
          </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Griffith, Farran, Okenden and Welsh </publisher>
               <pubPlace> London </pubPlace>
               <date> 1889 </date>
           </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> <q>Austral</q> [Wilson, Anne Glenny]. <q>The Forty-Mile Bush.</q> <hi rend="italic">Themes and Variations</hi> (London: Griffith, Farran, Okenden and Welsh, 1889), pp. 46-47. </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> Transcribed and encoded as part of "Settler Literature and Environmental Change in Australia and New Zealand," Marsden Fund Standard Grant 19-MAU-022 (Te Apārangi Royal Society of New Zealand). </p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
       <body>
           <lg>
               <l> Far through the forest’s<note> Forest. The Forty-Mile Bush was an area of dense forest in the Wairarapa region, on the opposite coast of the North Island to Wilson’s home, which was cleared during the 1870s and 1880s in large part by Scandinavian settlers brought to New Zealand by assisted migration schemes. </note> aromatic glade </l>
               <l> We rode one afternoon of golden ease. </l>
               <l> The long road ran through sunshine and through shade, </l>
               <l> Lulled by the somnolent stories of the trees. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Sometimes a bell-bird<note> Bell-bird. The bellbird/korimako is known for the clear ringing notes of its call. </note> fluted far away; </l>
               <l> Sometimes the murmur of the leafy deep, </l>
               <l> Rising and falling through the autumnal day, </l>
               <l> Sang louder on the hills, then sank to sleep. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Before us stretched the pine trees’<note>   Pine trees. The reference is unclear as several indigenous tree species that grew in the area were described as pines, notably rimu (red pine) and matai (black pine). </note> sombre miles, </l>
               <l> Soft lay the moss, like furs upon the floor. </l>
               <l> Behind, the woodland’s green monotonous aisles, </l>
               <l> Closed far away by sunset’s amber door. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> League after league the same. The sky grew red, </l>
               <l> And through the trees appeared a snowy gleam </l>
               <l> Of lonely peak and spectral mountain-head, </l>
               <l> And gulfs that nurse the glacier and the stream. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Deep in the glen, the merry waters racing </l>
               <l> Sent forth their turbulent voices to the night. </l>
               <l> The stars above began their solemn pacing, </l>
               <l> And home-like shone the distant village light.<note> Village light. The two major settlements in the Forty Mile Bush area were Mauriceville and Eketāhuna. </note> </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> Mysterious forest! In this humming city<note> City. The reference is unclear, as Wilson had been educated in Melbourne, but since her marriage in 1874 had lived on a cattle farm in the rural Rangitikei region of the North Island of New Zealand. </note> </l>
               <l> I seem to hear thy music-breathing tree, </l>
               <l> Thy branches wave and beckon me in pity, </l>
               <l> To seek again thy hospitality! </l>
           </lg>
       </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
                   
