<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
           <titleStmt>
               <title> <q>The Gentle River</q> </title>
               <author> John MacLennan </author>
           </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
              <edition>Transcribed and edited by Philip Steer</edition>
          </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Whitcombe and Tombs </publisher>
                <pubPlace> Christchurch </pubPlace>
                <date> 1907 </date>
           </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> MacLennan, John. <q>The Gentle River.</q> <hi rend="italic">Neptune’s Toll and Other Verses</hi> (Christchurch: Whitcombe and Tombs, 1907), pp. 50. </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> Transcribed and encoded as part of "Settler Literature and Environmental Change in Australia and New Zealand," Marsden Fund Standard Grant 19-MAU-022 (Te Apārangi Royal Society of New Zealand). </p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
       <body>
           <lg>
               <l> I know a certain valley<note> Valley. Possibly the valley of the Water of Leith, or the Leith River, which flows through the South Island city of Dunedin. </note> where the birch<note> Birch. Likely a reference to species of beech, which were originally mistaken for a species of birch, and predominated in hilly and mountainous forests, especially in the South Island. </note> and rata<note> Rata. A species of tree that produces red flowers during the summer. </note> lend </l>
               <l> Their stately form and colour to the sky, </l>
               <l> Where brambles deck the hollow and ferns<note> Ferns. There are almost two hundred species of fern native to New Zealand, and New Zealand’s forests are unusual due to the dominance of fern species. </note> in grandeur bend </l>
               <l> To kiss the gentle stream that eddies by. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> I know a rugged footpath where a crazy little bridge </l>
               <l> Is built alone to bear the weight of love, </l>
               <l> Or glass its rustic beauty in the waters of the ridge, </l>
               <l> Or shade them from the azure light above. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> I know a sweet November where morning glory<note> Morning glory. Pōwhiwhi, or the New Zealand bindweed, is a perennial vine that grows on forest margins and produces white flowers. The invasive blue morning glory was not introduced into New Zealand until the mid-twentieth century. </note> creeps </l>
               <l> Around the heart to while its care away; </l>
               <l> A fallen forest monarch entombed in emerald sleeps </l>
               <l> Where lovers rest to dream their sweet to-day. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> I know these things are transient, for winter comes anon </l>
               <l> To claim as withered leaves the rata bud; </l>
               <l> But yet a little summer till its loveliness is gone </l>
               <l> And gentle streams be ruffled by the flood. </l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
               <l> But I know another valley where frost shall never come, </l>
               <l> Where rata’s crimson blossoms never die; </l>
               <l> For fern and mossy valley in memory have a home </l>
               <l> Eternal as the stream that eddies by. </l>
           </lg>
       </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
                   